Guide to the Brenton Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Brenton correspondence
1819-1836
OSB MSS 35
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.25
(1 box)
Letters to Brenton regarding his book, "The Naval History of Great Britain." Mainly compliments to Brenton on the book. Some express interest in purchasing it, and some offer to give further information to help his research. Some, including George Cockburn, James De Saumarez, Richard Keats, and David Milne, include further information in their letters.
Brenton, Edward Pelham, 1774-1839
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of materials pertaining to Edward Pelham Brenton.
Naval history of Great Britain, from the year MDCCLXXXIII to MDCCCXXII; Great Britain -- History, Naval -- 18th century; Great Britain -- History, Naval -- 19th century; Brenton, Edward Pelham, 1774-1839; Cockburn, George, Sir, 1772-1853; De Saumarez, James Saumarez, Baron, 1757-1836; Keats, Richard Goodwin, Sir, 1757-1834; Milne, David, Sir, 1763-1845
- Correspondence, 1836 Jul 16
  - Brougham and Vaux, Henry Brougham, 1st Baron, 1778-1868. Letter (3d person) to Edward Pelham Brenton, Harrington, 1836 Jul 16 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cockburn, Sir George, Bart, 1772-1853. ALS to Edward Pelham Brenton, Admiralty, 1822 Oct 6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Derby, Edward Stanley, 12th Earl of, 1752-1834. Letter (3d person) to Edward Pelham Brenton, Grosvenor House, 1823 Feb 26 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - De Saumarez, James Saumarez, 1st Baron, 1757-1836. ALS to Edward Pelham Brenton, Saumarez, Guernsey, 1821 Aug 30 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Scope and Contents
    Admiral Saumarez writes concerning his command during 1801 in Algeziras Bay and in the Baltic, 1808-13.
  - Exmouth, Edward Pellew, 1st Viscount, 1757-1833. ALS to Edward Pelham Brenton, Plymouth, 1819 Aug 5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Grenville, Thomas, 1755-1846. ALS, 2 AL to Edward Pelham Brenton, Dropmore, Cleveland Square, 1822-23 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hardwicke, Charles Philip Yorke, 4th Earl of, 1799-1873. ALS to Edward Pelham Brenton, 1823 Mar 23 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    York sets an appointment for conversation with Brenton.
  - Keats, Sir Richard Goodwin, 1757-1834. ALS to Edward Pelham Brenton, Greenwich, 1824 Feb 25 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Accompanied by memorandum, holograph, signed, of 1824 Feb 31 outlining the voyages of the Superb during 1805-6 under Admiral Duckworth.
  - Keith, George Leith Elphinstone, Viscount, 1746-1823. ALS to Edward Pelham Brenton, Kincasdine, 1819 Aug 9 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Keith offers Brenton access to his papers.
  - Knighton, Sir William, Bart, 1776-1836. 2 ALS to Edward Pelham Brenton, Windsor Lodge and Pavilion, 1822 Oct 14, 1823 Jan 27 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Knighton was, in 1822-23, private secretary and keeper of the privy purse to King George IV.
  - Milne, Sir David, 1763-1845. ALS to to Edward Pelham Brenton, Inveresk, by Edinburgh, 1823 Aug 8 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Spencer, George John Spencer, 2nd Earl of, 1758-1834. ALS, AL to Edward Pelham Brenton, Northampton and St. James's Place, 1822 Oct 18, 1823 Mar 15 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Spencer orders a subscription to Brenton's Naval History, and, in the latter note, thanks Brenton for the portrait of Lord St. Vincent.
  - St. Vincent, John Jervis, Earl of, 1735-1823. ALS to Edward Pelham Brenton, Mortimer Street., 1810 Nov 17 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - William IV, King of Great Britain, 1765-1837. ALS to Edward Pelham Brenton, Bagshot, 1821 Jun 28 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    William, then Duke of Clarence, asks to subscribe to Brenton's work.
  - William Frederick, Duke of Gloucester, 1776-1834. ALS to Edward Pelham Brenton, Chilton Lodge, 1821 Dec 12 (Box 1, Folder 15)